{"tossups": [{"question": "An independence movement in this modern-day country started when Carlos Cespedes freed all his slaves and proclaimed the October 10th Manifesto. This country\u2019s anthem<em> \u201dLa Bayamesa\u201d</em> was composed during the Ten Years War. Valeriano Weyler was called \u201cthe Butcher\u201d after his brutal suppression of rebels in this modern-day country. Jos\u00b4e Mart\u00b4\u0131 was killed fighting for independence from Spain for, for ten points, what Caribbean island nation with its capital at Havana?", "answer": "Republic of<b> Cuba</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This leader established a national inquiry into the status of MMIW in his country. This prime minister, who ran on the slogan \u201cReal Change,\u201d has been accused by Jody Wilson-Raybould of obstruction of justice. This man expelled Jane Philpott from his party in 2019 over the SNC-Lavalin scandal. This man responded \u201cbecause it\u2019s 2015\u201d when asked why gender parity was important to his cabinet. For 10 points, name this current Prime Minister of Canada.", "answer": "<b> J</b>ustin<b> Trudeau</b> (prompt on \u201cTrudeau\u201d)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "A series of lawsuits brought by this man\u2019s heirs were known as his namesake<em> pleitos</em>. This man was granted royal titles and a tenth of the riches he discovered in the<em> Capitulations of Santa Fe</em>. This man\u2019s expedition was chronicled in<em> The Life of the Admiral</em>. The Bay of Arrows was named by this man after he was attacked by the Ciguayos people in the first of his voyages to Hispaniola. Ferdinand and Isabella commissioned the voyages of, for ten points, what navigator who is often credited with \u201cdiscovering\u201dAmerica?", "answer": "Christopher<b> Columbus</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "After Offa of Mercia offered a marriage between this man\u2019s daughter Bertha and Ecgfrith, this man banned English ships from his ports. This man\u2019s brother Carloman allied against him with the Lombard King Desiderius. Lupo II of Gascony may have helped ambush his men at the Roncevaux Pass, in which his chronicler Einhard noted every soldier was killed. This man\u2019s sons divided his empire after he died in the Treaty of Verdun. The son of Pepin the Short, for ten points, name this first Holy Roman Emperor.", "answer": "<b> Charlemagne</b> (Or<b> Charles</b> the Great, or<b> Carolus Magnus</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The book The Destiny of The Mother Church is controversial in this sect for comparing this sect\u2019s founder to Jesus Christ. Mark Twain wrote a book about this sect in which he breaks 102 bones and isn\u2019t treated. Members of this sect believe that they can be cursed by \u201cmalicious animal magnetism\u201d and collect books in their \u201creading rooms.\u201d For ten points, name this sect, founded by Mary Baker Eddy, which publishes a namesake \u201cMonitor\u201d and believes sickness is an illusion curable by prayer.", "answer": "<b> Christian Science</b> Page 1", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "The SSNIP test checks for violations of this type of legislation. \u201cTying\u201d claims are often made citing this type of legislation. The case of<em> Flood v. Kuhn</em> upheld the exception granted to Major League Baseball from this type of legislation. The<em> E.C. Knight</em> ruling weakened a law of this type that had been passed in 1890. For ten points, name this type of law that guarantees fair competition as a benefit to consumers, two of which are named for Clayton and Sherman.", "answer": "<b> antitrust</b> acts", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man controversially placed bishop Aloysius Stepinac under house arrest where he died. This man secured power after executing Draza Mihailovic, the leader of the Chetnik Movement, for collaborating with the Ustase [oo-sta-shuh]. During the Informbiro period, this man\u2019s disagreements with Joseph Stalin led his country to be expelled from Cominform. The Non-Aligned Movement was co-founded by this Partisan leader. For ten points, identify this marshal who led communist Yugoslavia.", "answer": "Josip Broz<b> Tito</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Pierre Pelletier and Joseph Caventou isolated and named the active agent of one cure for this disease over 100 years after that cure was first introduced to Europe by the Jesuits from the Andes. Because this disease\u2019s merozoites infect and travel via red blood cells, sickle cell anemia provides moderate resistance against, for ten points, what disease which is increasingly resistant to quinine and is caused by<em> Plasmodium</em> parasites carried by<em> Anopholes</em> mosquitoes?", "answer": "<b> malaria</b>", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {}, {"question": "The first holder of this position wrote down verses from Sophocles\u2019<em> Ajax</em> before jumping out a window at the National Naval Medical Center. Another holder of this position, James Schlesinger, was dismissed in part due to lying about carrying out tactical strikes during the<em> Mayaguez</em> incident. Robert McNamara held this position for over 2,000 days, allowing him to oversee the majority of the Vietnam War. The National Security Act of 1947 merged the Navy and War Departments to create, for ten points, what Cabinet position that oversees the armed forces?", "answer": "<b> Secretary of Defense</b> (accept<b> SecDef</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "It was last ruled by Muhammad XII and earlier, its Sultan Yusuf I supported a Marinid Invasion at the Battle of R\u00b4\u0131o Salado.", "answer": "<b> Granada</b> Page 3", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This California explorer ruled autocratically over the Department of the West in 1861.", "answer": "John C.<b> Fremont</b> Page 4", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Father Henry Garnet was unable to warn this event\u2019s target because Catholic law forbade him from revealing confessionals. This event\u2019s planners attempted to fight off arrest during a gun battle at Holbeche House. An anonymous letter to Lord Monteagle revealed the details of this event. Robert Catesby was arrested for planning this event, in which 36 barrels of explosives were found in the House of Lords. For ten points, identify this event where Guy Fawkes tried to blow up Parliament.", "answer": "<b> Gunpowder Plot</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In Jan Hooks\u2019 portrayal of this woman, Phil Hartman plays her husband and she fights a politician played by Dan Aykroyd. Vanessa Bayer, Ana Gasteyer, and Amy Poehler are among the actresses who have portrayed this woman, whose more recent appearances have been accompanied by Cecily Strong as Huma Abedin and Tom Hanks as a debate moderator. For ten points, name this politician who, as played by Kate McKinnon, has taken part in presidential debates against Alec Baldwin\u2019s Donald Trump on<em> Saturday Night Live</em>.", "answer": "(Saturday Night Live\u2019s version of) Hillary<b> Rodham Clinton</b> (accept either or both underlined parts)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Abraham Lincoln asked Charlotte Cushman to see her play this character from his favorite Shakspearian play, which had been her first dramatic role. In Act 1 Scene 7, this</b> <b>character reassures another \u201cscrew your (+)</b> <b>courage to the sticking-place, and we\u2019ll not</b> <b>fail.\u201d While sleepwalking, this character cries \u201cYet who would have thought the old man to have had so much (*)</b> blood in him\u201d while trying to clean the \u201cdamned spot\u201d from her hands. For ten points, name this Shakespearean character who helped her husband murder the Scottish King Duncan.", "answer": "<b> Lady Macbeth</b> (accept descriptions of<b> Macbeth\u2019s wife</b>; do not prompt on \u201cMacbeth\u201d alone)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Drama"}, {"question": "<b>This battle was preceded by the fall of Fort St. John which nearly resulted in the capture of Guy Carleton. Daniel Morgan was one of over 300 soldiers to be captured in this battle. (+) Benedict Arnold was shot in the leg during this battle, hours after leading troops across the (*) </b> Plains of Abraham. In the winding hours of this battle, Aaron Burr attempted to recover the body of Richard Montgomery who had, days prior, captured Montreal. For ten points, name this crushing 1775 defeat which ended the American invasion of Canada.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Quebec</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Dead Horse Camp was established by an explorer traveling on this river. One explorer of this river was believed to be immortal and during an eclipse, was given gifts by the (+) Aisuari people to not extinguish the sun. Samuel Fritz helped preach to the Cambeba people who lived along this river. In his search for the (*)</b> \u201cLost City of Z\u201d, Percy Fawcett travelled down this river into the Mato Grosso region. Tapuya women fighting alongside men helped give this river its name. For ten points, name this river that crosses a massive rainforest in Brazil.", "answer": "<b> Amazon</b> River", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>In 1663, a Great Fire destroyed most of this city, including a shrine to Mazu. Portuguese Jesuits ruled this city for seven years after it was ceded to them by (+) Dom Bartolomeu. A Dutch trading post on the island of Dejima in this city was the only location open to (*) </b>Westerners during the Edo Period. This city was targeted for one attack after Henry Stimson removed his honeymoon destination, Kyoto, from a target list. The bomber Bockscar dropped Fat Man on, for ten points, what second Japanese city to be hit by an atomic bomb, three days after Hiroshima?", "answer": "<b> Nagasaki</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>In one work, Pierre-Joseph Proudhon asked what is this concept, only to respond that it is theft. In</b><em><b> Discourse on Inequality</b></em><b>, Rousseau claimed that the first person to create this concept \u201cand [find] people simple enough to believe him\u201d was the founder of (+) civil society. That work argues against the</b><em><b> Second Treatise on Government</b></em><b>, where Locke argued that this concept was justified by a person\u2019s (*) </b> labor in creating value and paired the right to this concept with the rights to life and liberty. For ten points, name this concept, where a person privately owns something.", "answer": "<b> property</b> Page 9", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b>In this state, Mary McLeod Bethune, inspired by the work of Lucy Laney in Georgia, opened a school for African-American girls. The president of this state\u2019s branch of the</b> <b>NAACP, Harry (+)</b> <b>Moore, was killed in a 1951 bombing orchestrated by the KKK. A</b> <b>white mob in this state killed Julius Perry for allegedly sheltering Mose Norman as part of the Ocoee massacre. In 1923, the entire town of (*)</b> Rosewood was burned to the ground in this state as part of rising racial tensions. For ten points, name this Southern state where lynchings often took place in Orlando.", "answer": "<b> Florida</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Susan Lindauer was arrested and detained based on this legislation, which resulted</b> <b>in Sami Al-Arian being deported to Turkey. (+)</b> <b>\u201cSneak and peek\u201d warrants were</b> <b>introduced in Title II of this legislation. Russ Feingold was the only Senator to</b> <b>vote against this legislation, which was broadcasted by Michael (*)</b> Moore in a rented ice-cream van on the streets of Washington, D.C. This legislation expanded National Security Letters and allowed the NSA to collect mass phone data. For 10 points, name this law passed by George W. Bush in 2001, a controversial anti-terrorism act.", "answer": "USA<b> PATRIOT</b> ACT", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}], "bonuses": []}